### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/hamzashahbaz-naeem-98325968 (LinkedIn)

### Top Skills

Business Intelligence
Data Analysis
Microsoft SQL Server

## Languages

Urdu

**English** 

### Certifications

Developing Microsoft SharePoint Server 2013 Core Solutions

# Hamza Shahbaz Naeem

Data Scientist at Speridian Technologies Orange County, California Area

## Summary

I'm an intuitive on-course computer science and data scientist with multiple expertise ranging from Data Mining, Statistical Analysis, Liner Non-Linear Models and Machine Learning. My expertise is in Business Intelligence, Data Analysis and SQL. I am highly focused on adhering to organizational missions and philosophy while positively impacting bottom line and daily performance.

A creative thinker with effective management abilities combined with leadership, interpersonal, and presentation skills. Self-motivated with the ability to excel in a fast-paced environment; communicate effectively at all levels; manage competing priorities; and adapt readily to new challenges.

Computer application and programming skills includes R, C#, ASP.NET, MSSQL and Python.

Project Management Tools: Jira, Stash, Bit Bucket, Source Tree.

I possess an extensive knowledge of ERP/BI life-cycle implementation complemented with a strong basis in Requirement gathering, Analysis, and Development. I have worked in object oriented programming, data gathering, data pre-processing and analysis. Very capable with the ability, drive and determination needed to succeed in winning business and creating opportunity.

I am familiar with protocols for handling sensitive information with desire and experience in assisting diverse populations with patience and understanding.

# Experience

Speridian Technologies
Data Scientist
September 2018 - Present (1 year 7 months)
Page 1 of 4

Vire Technologies

4 years 2 months

Lead Data Analyst

June 2015 - January 2017 (1 year 8 months)

Pakistan

- •Led a team of 10 professionals including developers, analyst and QA professionals that worked with development and management teams in Chicago, IL.
- •Successfully developed and redesigned PSCU portal to deliver payment solutions to Credit Unions across the USA, partnered with credit unions to provide the highest quality payment options, fraud prevention, digital solutions, loyalty rewards, data analytics programs,
- •Designed and implemented new software solution that resulted in an overall partner's firm revenue increase of 20%.
- •Acted as single point of contact between organization management and appropriate client or groups from solution planning, sizing, to fulfillment.
- •Developed data mining technique (Associate Rule Mining) to predict satisfactorily the products customers buy together.
- •Improved customer experience by using clustering algorithms like KNN to give actionable and quantified suggestions to credit unions resulting in improved sales, additional accounts and \$15MM profit annually.
- •Used ensemble methods: Bagging, Boosting, Random Forest to improve predictive performance.
- •Determined and provided a necessary level of technical documentation during requirements gathering, based on technical services group standards and procedures.
- •Analyzed data for Credit Unions & Retail Industry containing but not limited to:
- -Buying patterns
- -P2C/C2P conversions
- -Targeted promotions and campaigns
- -Frequency of account usage.
- -Market Basket Analysis (association rules)
- -Sales data
- -Point of sale data
- -Gross margins and revenue
- -Market share
- -Competitor pricing

- -Promotional and marketing data
- -ROI on promotion
- -Loyalty
- -Merchandising data

Data Analyst- BI February 2014 - May 2015 (1 year 4 months) Pakistan

Worked with Microsoft Center of Excellence in the region to provide consultancy on Microsoft Office BI suite. Worked with a team of 4 people over multiple projects. The responsibilities included:

- •Reporting & Visualization: Recognize organization needs and develop visualizations using SSRS, Tableau, R and PowerBI to provide valuable insights.
- •Data Analysis: Analyze data concerning the market trends and competitive standards and draw conclusions from organization's perspective. Create and iterate on solutions and dashboards to empower operational and exploratory analysis
- •Predictive Analytics: Used clustering algorithm like KNN to segregate and categorize farming products and analyze products quality and provide route optimization to maximize shelf-life of perishable goods.
- •Enforce best practices and alignment with research, forecasting, analytics, and engineering teams

Software Developer December 2012 - May 2014 (1 year 6 months) Lahore, Pakistan

- •Worked on web-based and desktop applications, including cloud and onpremise development.
- •Contributed my software engineering expertise in the development of products through the software lifecycle, from requirements definition through to successful deployment.

Xelleration Software Engineer April 2012 - December 2012 (9 months) Lahore, Pakistan

•Software Developer with majority of my work related to Microsoft SharePoint development.

- •Responsible for In-House development as well as direct correspondence with clients.
- •Correspondence with clients included requirement gathering, development and maintenance as well active communication to keep the clients engaged.
- •Worked work on various BI Tools such as PowerPivot, SSIS, SSAS and SSRS.
- Created automated workflows in SharePoint Designer Workflows for management tools and HelpDesk activities.
- •Dashboard Designing using PerformancePoint Services

## Education

The University of Chicago

Master of Science (MS), Analytics · (2017 - 2018)

Lahore University of Management Sciences
Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Computer Science (2007 - 2011)

Garrison Academy for Boys (1992 - 2007)